NAVEEN N RAVI

250 East 6th Street, Apt 0804 \diamond Saint Paul, MN 55101 (832) \cdot 720 \cdot 2393 \diamond nravi.research@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Professional Software Engineer with experience in the general areas of parallel and distributed computing. Specifically, my technical skills focuses in the following areas: (i) parallel programming models and runtime systems (MPI and PGAS models like OpenSHMEM, Global Arrays, and Coarray Fortran); (ii) parallel computing architectures, and (iii) high-speed interconnects

EXPERIENCE

Hewlett Packard Enterprise

Jan,2020 - present

 $Systems/Software\ Engineer\ -\ Programming\ Environment\ Message\ Passing\ Toolkit\ Bloomington,\ MN$

Cray, Inc Dec,2015 - Dec,2019

Software Engineer - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit Bloomington, MN

- · HPC and parallel programming runtime optimizations for HPE/Cray supercomputer and cluster hardware to be utilized by specific customers like U.S government and commercial petroleum industries
- · Work specifically on Cray software stacks like Cray MPICH and Cray SHMEM
- · Participate and represent HPE/Cray in OpenSHMEM and MPI standards committee

Cray, Inc May, 2015 - Dec, 2015

Intern - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul, MN

- · Research, Prototype, and Implement new features in Cray SHMEM programming library
- · Optimize Global Arrays library for NAMD and NWChem Chemistry applications

University of Houston

Sep,2013 - May,2015

Research Assistant - HPC Tools

Houston, TX

- · Research Assistant to Dr.Barbara Chapman
- · Research and explore strategies for runtime optimizations, and compiler-tools interactions for large-scale parallel systems using OpenSHMEM and Coarray Fortran programming models

EDUCATION

University of Minnesota, Twin Cities

Aug, 2022

Ph.D. in Computer Science

University of Houston, Main Campus

Aug, 2013 - Dec, 2015

M.S. in Computer Science - Specialization in Parallel & Distributed Systems

Anna University, India

Sep,2007 - May,2011

Bachelors in Engineering - Electrical & Electronics Engineering

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Programming Languages C/C++, Fortran, Python

Parallel Programming Models OpenSHMEM, MPI, Coarray Fortran, OpenMP

Network Libraries DMAPP, Verbs, Libfabric System Architectures Aarch64, x86_64, GPU

Architectures Cray Supercomputers, & Clusters, Intel MIC

AWARDS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- 1. Best Paper Award, 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Model(PGAS 2014).
- 2. Graduate Assistant Tution Fellowship, September 2013 May 2015.
- 3. Best Undergraduate Student Project, Mepco Schlenk Eng. College, Anna University, India, 2011.

PROJECTS

Current Projects

1. Cray OpenSHMEMX

- Cray OpenSHMEMX, a new OpenSHMEM library implementation that supersedes the existing production ready Cray SHMEM library on future exascale Cray Shasta architectures
- Design and develop Cray OpenSHMEMX from scratch with support for different transport layers including DMAPP, XPMEM, and Libfabric

2. Cray MPICH

- Introduce advanced GPU-awareness using GPU Async features
- Create an optimized message matching layer for the MPI implementation

REFEREED CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

My full name is **Naveen Namashivayam Ravichandrasekaran** and I author all conference and workshop publications as **Naveen Namashivayam**.

- 1. T.Groves, **N.Namashivayam**, B.Cook, B.Friesen, N.Keen, D.Trebotich, N.J.Wright, B.Alverson, D.Roweth, and K.Underwood. "Not All Applications Have Boring Communication Patterns: Profiling Message Matching with BMM". In Proceedings of Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience.
- 2. **N.Namashivayam**, S.Mehta, and P.C.Yew. "Variable-sized Blocks for Locality-aware SpMV". In Proceedings of International Symposium on Code Generation and Optimization (CGO 2021).
- 3. **N.Namashivayam**, B.Long, D.Eachempati, B.Cernohous, and M.Pagel. "A Modern Fortran Interface in OpenSHMEM.". In Proceedings of ACM Transactions on Parallel Computing, August, 2020.
- 4. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, D.Pou, and M.Pagel. "Introducing Cray OpenSHMEMX A Modular Multi-Communication Layer OpenSHMEM Implementation.". In Proceedings of Fifth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies, August, 2018, Hanover, USA.
- 5. **N.Namashivayam**, B.Cernohous, K.Kandalla, D.Pou, J.Robichaux, J.Dinan, and M.Pagel. "Symmetric Memory Partitions in OpenSHMEM: A case study with Intel KNL". In Proceedings of Fourth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Big Compute and Big Data Convergence, August, 2017, Annapolis, USA.
- 6. K.Kandalla, P.Mendygral, N.Radcliffe, B.Cernohous, **N.Namashivayam**, K.McMahon, C.Sadlo and M.Pagel "Current State of the Cray MPT Software Stacks on the Cray XC Series Supercomputers". In proceedings of Cray User Group Meeting, 2017, Redmond, USA.
- 7. N.Namashivayam, D.Knaak, B.Cernohous, N.Radcliffe, and M.Pagel. "An Evaluation of Thread-Safe and Contexts-Domains Features in Cray SHMEM". In Proceedings of Third Workshop on

- OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Enhancing OpenSHMEM for Hybrid Environments, August, 2016, Hanover, USA.
- 8. N.Namashivayam, D.Eachempati, D.Khaldi and B.Chapman. "OpenSHMEM as a Portable Communication Layer for PGAS Models A Case Study with Coarray Fortran". In Proceedings of IEEE Cluster 2015, September, 2015, Chicago, USA.
- 9. **N.Namashivayam**, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati and B.Chapman. "Extending the Strided Communication Interface in OpenSHMEM". In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, USA.
- 10. D.Knaak, and **N.Namashivayam**. "Proposing OpenSHMEM Extensions Towards a Future for Hybrid Programming and Heterogeneous Computing", In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, USA.
- 11. **N.Namashivayam**, S.Ghosh, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati, and B.Chapman. "Native Mode-Based Optimizations of Remote Memory Accesses in OpenSHMEM for Intel Xeon Phi", 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Models (PGAS 2014).

THESIS

• N.Namashivayam. "OpenSHMEM as an Effective Communication Layer for PGAS Models". Master's Thesis, University of Houston, October, 2015.

KEY ACTIVITIES

Standardization efforts

- 1. OpenSHMEM standardization Effort, Participate and represent HPE in OpenSHMEM standards committee. http://openshmem.org/.
- 2. MPI Forum, Participate and represent HPE in the standardization forum for the Message Passing Interface (MPI).

Program Committees

- 1. Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies 2016, 2017, 2018, and 2021.
- 2. IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems (TPDS).